<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Biography of a Bipolar</title>
    <description>I write about life with Type 1 Bipolar Disorder. Background in IT, pursuing  my Bachelor of Science in Nursing and passionate about health informatics
</description>
    <link>/biography-of-a-bipolar//</link>
    <atom:link href="/biography-of-a-bipolar//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 17:25:03 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 17:25:03 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.5.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Confessions Of A Cynic</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;How old do you have to be before you’re allowed to be a cynic? How much life do you have to experience before you’re allowed to determine that life is not all it’s cracked up to be? I suppose it’s all rather relative. For some, it seems they live their entire lives completely naive of the hardships faced by so many people. For me, it was probably around the time I graduated high school. I grew up in a very tiny school - my graduating class was less than 60 students. The first “week” of school was always spent at a retreat-style camp, getting to know teachers and classmates alike. It was, for the most part, a decent experience. But my senior year redefined life for many students and teachers. Avoiding all the details, a classmate of mine drowned during our senior retreat. His death hurled myself and my fellow classmates into a world that so many of our parents tried to protect us from. Your senior year of high school is supposed to be a time of jubilance and rejoicing – but for the handful of graduating seniors that year, there was little to celebrate. Despite our best efforts to deny our vulnerability, as a 17 or 18 year old, we are still very pliable. One of the defining moments of my childhood was watching teachers that I looked up to – teachers that I respected – lose composure and weep. When you’re a student, it’s easy to overlook the fact that these beings, who are supposed to teach you something, are, in fact, human too. I think for many, the transition out of childhood is a long, sometimes subtle one. But I clearly and vividly remember the moment that I stopped being a child. That moment, looking around thinking, “Oh my God - this is actually happening.” That moment when I saw terror on the faces of those whom I looked up to for so many years. The moment when I realized that there was absolutely nothing I could do to alleviate the pain others were experiencing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often say, “Kids are resilient; they bounce back from tragedies.” But what happens when that tragedy rips away the very innocence that defines a child? I contend that losing your childhood innocence and becoming a cynic are two different things. Yes, I was thrust into the world of death and misery very quickly and, by many accounts, far too early. But like any story worth telling, there was a girl. Two girls, actually. I won’t go all, “Woe is me” on you – but let’s just say that the old saying, “The first cut is the deepest” holds pretty true. In fact, after my first real heartbreak, I would have said that there was no way I would ever experience pain like that again. Sweet, sweet, naive me from the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve yet to find an instruction manual on living with Bipolar Disorder. When you’re dealing with feelings of depression so intense that – I’m sorry to say unless you’ve experienced, you just can’t understand (even the most empathetic) – trying to maintain a healthy relationship can be next to impossible. Dealing with the onset of Bipolar Disorder caused me to lose sight of just about everything in my life. I lost a woman I was in love with, lost my intentions of education, many days I lost the will to live. By the ripe age of 25, I had witnessed death far too often. I understand that in wanting to be a nurse, I will inevitably lose patients. I’ve watched death slowly tear a mother away from her family, steal away a 17-year old who was likely one of the happiest people I’ve ever known, and some days I’ve wrestled with death so intensely that it feels like going 12-rounds with a heavy-weight champion. I often wonder if people understand what it is like to lay in bed for 17 hours, and be so exhausted when you finally do get up that all you want to do is sleep because you have been literally fighting for your life against the hardest opponent you will ever face – yourself. I was classically trained in policy debate. I’ve been taught how to be presented a resolution and to equally defend and oppose my positions. I was trained by a very well-respected coach and was lucky enough to face some of the toughest competition in the nation. This has made me a better person because I can simply no longer just see one side of an argument. However, those nights where I’d be trying to figure out why I was still alive, it made for one hell of a showdown in my mind. I could always negate the idea of life – I had been trained to do so. I suppose on the flip side of the coin, I was also countering death with very solid reasons for life. In some respects, I think, had I not been blessed with the critical analysis training I went through in high school, I’d likelybe dead, as I would have lost the debate in my mind to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this has given me some insights into our world and the lives we lead. First, there aren’t enough Snickers in this world because life, most of the time, for most of the near 8 billion people on the planet, is shit. Some will say that it’s elitist to say that as I write this on my laptop in my air-conditioned apartment, while there is genocide and mass poverty around the world. But, life is more than the sum of our belongings. I’d gladly give away all of my possessions if I could live a fulfilling life. (Note I didn’t say a happy life – I specifically said fulfilled life. There’s another post coming on my views of happiness. Spoiler alert: I’m not too big on the idea.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rose Kennedy once said, “It has been said, ‘time heals all wounds.’ I do not agree. The wounds remain. In time, the mind, protecting its sanity, covers them with scar tissue and the pain lessens. But it is never gone.” I’d like to expand on that quote, but it is so well written I think it really speaks for itself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/biography-of-a-bipolar//posts/confessions-of-a-cynic</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/biography-of-a-bipolar//posts/confessions-of-a-cynic</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Masochism And The Road Less Traveled</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The path of least resistance. What an interesting thing. Water, electricity, basically everything takes it… so why can’t I?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Merriam-Webster:
 &lt;strong&gt;Masochism&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;em&gt;enjoyment of pain : pleasure&lt;/em&gt;
 &lt;em&gt;that someone gets from being abused or hurt.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being diagnosed with Bipolar Disorder has been an interesting ride. Some days I feel like I can manage it better than others (I guess that’s part of the gig, right?). It definitely forced me to reconsider my career choice. I had struggled for years in determining what I wanted to do. I often bounced between being a nurse and working in the IT field. I even considered working in the healthcare IT field, but eventually came to the conclusion that I wanted to be solely in the medical field. As I was working through my pre-nursing classes I had the opportunity to travel to Brazil and spend a week traveling down the Rio Negro on a hospital boat aiding and learning from two surgeons and some nurses in treating various remote villages. It was a life changing experience in so many ways. I knew I didn’t just want to be a nurse, I wanted to be a doctor. But as my history has proven, I was a little indecisive. I continued my pre-nursing classes and when the time came to apply to nursing school I was not accepted (The school I was applying to had a very backwards admissions criteria – on paper I was a solid candidate. It was &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; backwards). But I took not being accepted as a definitive sign that medical school was where I was supposed to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I transferred to the University of Central Florida and started taking classes in the College of Medicine’s School of Biomedical Sciences. Unfortunately, my bipolar disorder began to really flare up and it caused me to very heavily reconsider my choice to be a doctor – medical school doesn’t play too nice with the inability to get out of bed for days or sleep for days (give or take). So I spun… out of control for a while. I eventually landed on my feet – in the College of Sciences, School of Psychology. The plan – earn my bachelor’s degree in psychology and then go to graduate school to earn my Doctorate of Psychology and practice clinically… practice what you may ask? I don’t know; which isn’t a problem. But there was a nagging. And for a while I didn’t care – I could get my medical fix with the beloved Dr. Gregory House and the worst written show on TV – Grey’s Anatomy (Seriously, the writing is SO FREAKING AWFUL… WHY CAN’T I STOP WATCHING?!?). As it turns out, fictional TV, awesome shows or otherwise, can’t fulfill real life. And after a while I realized that I want to be a doctor… of medicine. Very badly. Even though becoming a doctor will likely be the &lt;em&gt;hardest&lt;/em&gt; thing I will ever do, I want it, more than anything. Just being in (or even near) a hospital invigorates me – it’s a rush of life that I can’t describe – it isn’t mania, it’s so much better than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not all sunshine and oranges (I’m a Floridian, it fits). Getting to the point of those two wonderful letters – M.D. – is a long road for even the healthiest of persons. And let’s be honest, Type 1 Bipolar Disorder means I’m a long way from healthy. It reminds me of a poem I once read in high school (my English would be so proud to know I &lt;strong&gt;did&lt;/strong&gt; take something out of those classes – it just &lt;em&gt;looked&lt;/em&gt; like I was sleeping). Robert Frost’s “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.poetryfoundation.org/poem/173536&quot; title=&quot;The Road Not Taken&quot;&gt;The Road Not Taken&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave you with this thought; what is it that you want most in this life? What are you doing to obtain it? I know what I want most – and I know that to get it, I will hurt; a lot. I will struggle, I will want to quit, I will be pushed to the edge but I know that if I don’t take that road, I will be selling myself short. Funny thing, that road is certainly not the path of least resistance and will certainly cause me massive amounts of pain – and I can’t imagine life any other way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/biography-of-a-bipolar//posts/masochism-and-the-road-less-traveled</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/biography-of-a-bipolar//posts/masochism-and-the-road-less-traveled</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inside My Manic Mind</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I often think people mis-conceptualize Bipolar Disorder. They hear it and think of a person who is kind and gentle, and then, out of the blue, they turn into The Hulk; almost a Dr. Jekyll / Mr. Hyde scenario. While it’s true during a manic episode some may become angry, I don’t think that is the typical response. Instead, I think it is much more common for one to become elated, euphoric, almost in a constant high state. They take on a sense of grandiosity, feeling they are invincible. Often they spend money at an alarming pace, sleep less, and make seemingly novel connections to completely unrelated items in life. That’s the textbook response for manic episodes, anyone can look up a textbook response, but as I write this, I’m coming off several weeks of mania, which can offer a much more intimate glimpse of what it means to be manic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to pin down exactly when my manic episodes start, but a good sign is my sleep schedule. I start going to bed later and later. First 12:30 am, then 1:15 am, 2:00 am, 5:00 am, 7;00 am, and finally, by the time I’m in full-blown mania, I’m not sleeping at night at all. The next sign is I start to think I can pick up old projects that I never finished and accomplish them. I never do restart them though, generally I move to a new idea too quickly. I may start that idea, or maybe I jump to another one. The ideas could be anything from learning some new web framework, or perhaps I decide to create a font (as of this writing I still haven’t finished that project) or maybe it’s something deeper. One of the biggest struggles my bipolar has caused is a severe inability to decide on a career path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next comes the racing thoughts. My mind starts to race and it becomes very hard to put together any serious, coherent thought. This has affected my ability to complete homework, take exams, sit still for long. I’ve gotten pretty efficient at writing my professors explaining what is going on; something I wish I didn’t have to do. I often wonder if my racing thoughts are similar to what those with ADHD experience. If it is, I greatly sympathize for them, because I know that, at some point for me the racing thoughts will fade, I can’t imagine living like that all the time. During my manic phases I often will get up to get a drink and by the time I get to the kitchen I forget why I’m there. Or worse, I’ll get sidetracked before even going to the kitchen and go there without my glass. In the past, I’ve actually gone from my room to the kitchen three times just to get a drink, simply because my mind was racing so fast that I couldn’t keep my thoughts straight enough, long enough to complete such a meaningless task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love to read. When I was younger my head was always buried in a book. In the fourth grade, I chose to do a book report on a Wishbone book. I checked out the book from the library, along with the VHS (before movies were digital downloads we had these things called DVD’s, BEFORE THOSE we had these things called VHS tapes. It’s hard to believe that I’ve reached the age where I actually need to explain what a VHS was. Is this what my parents felt like about vinyl!?). When I got in the car, my mom saw both the book and tape and asked about them. I told her it was for a book report - her response was something like, “oh great, you’ve already figured out that trick.” I had no idea what she was talking about, I just loved Wishbone. In fact, I was already nose deep into the book (Admittedly, I totally used that method later in high school). By the time I reached high school I had moved from fiction to legal case studies and legislation. And finally, by my undergraduate years, my reading consisted of (and still does) academic journals, technical white papers, 1000 page textbooks, and that is what I read for fun. But when I’m manic I can’t get through a simple news article. It sucks. I can’t take 3 weeks off from my reading and expect to stay ahead, or at least on par in my classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess, road rage scares me; too often I see stories on the news of needless violence because of it. Because of this, I’m a fairly safe and conservative driver. That all changes when I’m manic. I drive faster, get irritated, curse people who drive slow, question the intelligence of the engineers who programmed the traffic lights,  and generally wonder why people don’t understand that every road I drive on was built specifically for my needs. This manic mentality is not good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my recent bouts of mania I’ve found myself drawing, sketching, painting. I’m not an artist, the science part of my brain usually outweighs the creative side. I also clean, which falls somewhere on the spectrum from, “My room is now clean and tidy, clothes washed, dried, folded, and put away” to, “I’ve gone through every box I own, reorganized, shuffled them around, ordered my closet by color and style and completed a head count of my socks.” Some may call this productive, others neurotic, regardless, they are definitely obsessive compulsive tendencies (luckily it doesn’t interfere with my daily activities yet, thankfully no OCD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far everything I’ve described severely lowers my productivity. However, there is usually a window, sometimes many days, sometimes a few hours, occasionally completely absent, where all previously said things intertwine at the perfect level and I become a person so productive you might wonder what drugs I was on. It’s breathtaking, inspiring, and all around freaking awesome. If I could live in that manic state at all times, I’d change the world in unimaginable ways. Unfortunately, that’s not how it works. It’s usually clockwork. I’m manic for a time and then, as if I’ve fallen off a cliff, I become so depressed that hospitalization usually comes up in my inner monologue, but I’ll save that for another blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;mark&gt;Mania can be a magical, fantastical, inspirational world, but more often it is a place I dread as much as my depression.&lt;/mark&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not often that my sleep schedule, ability to focus, and my slightly obsessive cleaning come into perfect alignment to make a Robert capable of anything. No, it’s far more likely you’ll find me severely impaired as a result of my inability to support a consistent sleep schedule, irrational anger at other drivers, hopelessly attempting to read, and obsessively cleaning. I was once asked if I enjoy the times when I’m manic, and my response was no, I do not enjoy it. Not only do I have to deal with all the issues I’ve written about, but there is a foreboding shadow of the darkness to come, and no matter what I do, I cannot escape that shadow because, as I’ve come to learn, that shadow is my own.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/biography-of-a-bipolar//posts/inside-my-manic-mind</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/biography-of-a-bipolar//posts/inside-my-manic-mind</guid>
        
        <category>mania</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>When Your Significant Other&lt;br&gt;Has Bipolar Disorder</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was recently asked a question on Twitter about being in a romantic relationship with someone diagnosed with Bipolar Disorder. Below is the original question and my response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My partner of 11 months was diagnosed with Bipolar Disorder (1) 6 months ago. We have argued quiet a bit recently, but even before the diagnosis we argued a bit about what I thought was trivial stuff and it has just worn me out. I don’t have the love I felt for her or the patience for it anymore. It’s not fair on her either but I feel selfish and guilty. We live together and have been arguing the past few days and I think it’s best that we break up for both our sakes as I don’t have empathy (not just for her) and I’m not a big talker about emotions and that. I just feel really lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s very common to feel lost and confused when someone significant in your life is diagnosed with any mental illness. As a society, we don’t really give mental illness the time of day, so a diagnosis can seem very scary for everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I think it’s very common to feel lost and confused when someone significant in your life is diagnosed with any mental illness. As a society, we don’t really give mental illness the time of day, so a diagnosis can seem very scary for everyone involved. It’s worth noting that there is a good chance she is feeling many of the same emotions that you are. Because the nature of Bipolar Disorder is so unstable, I spend a lot of time trying to figure out if there was some specific trigger that cause a depressive or manic episode. Honestly, I rarely find a trigger, which leaves me dazed and confused. Bipolar Disorder 1 is far more intense than any other form of the disease and I imagine handling the mood swings can be really challenging and tiring. I fight exhaustion on a regular basis, as I’m sure anyone does who is affected so deeply by Bipolar Disorder; be it the diagnosed or those surrounding them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cornerstone to any relationship is communication. Tell your significant other how you feel. It’s always better to put all the cards on the table for both of you to see. Imagine that your emotional state is a radio wave coming from your iPhone, it has peaks and it has valleys. Maybe it looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;small-wave&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a person suffering with Bipolar Disorder it may look like this: big-wave&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, unless you’re dating Spock, those intense changes in emotion are going to bleed through to every aspect of life and likely cause some tension; even what may seem like trivial things can cause this tension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research shows sex cures all “&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/APA&quot;&gt;@APA&lt;/a&gt;: Sexual intimacy makes couples optimistic even when facing physical, other issues &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/q4QUF9UbhV&quot;&gt;http://t.co/q4QUF9UbhV&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Aaron Kraus (@Aaron_Kraus) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Aaron_Kraus/status/440981483977592832&quot;&gt;March 4, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many, empathy does not come naturally or easily. Society has this (in my opinion, irrational) rule that men can’t talk about their emotions. However, you kind of have to talk about emotions to better empathize with someone, there isn’t a way around that; if you want to better understand what someone is going through emotionally, discussing those emotions is inherently necessary. Pushing yourself out of your comfort box generally helps you grow as a person, give it a try, you may find that talking about emotions isn’t as bad as you had once thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stayed in a relationship out of guilt for several months. I felt like it would be selfish of me to end the relationship because she was going through a health issue. I remember a conversation with one of my mentors about it, and he told me to not be a hero, it’s not healthy. Of course, at the time I was convinced that it would be ok, I could be the healthy hero. He was right (mentors generally are). Years later, I was again faced with a situation where I found my significant other facing incredible turbulence. Again, my mentor advised me not to be a hero – things would not end well for either of us. But this time was different, I didn’t feel like I was being a hero; I had real feelings for her and was ready to stand by her and get her through the tough times. Looking back I now acknowledge two vastly different emotional responses. With the first, I wanted to be the hero; I glamorized the idea and thought that it would earn me some brownie points. The second situation, I just wanted to be there for her, out of love, nothing else. Evaluate your feelings; where on the spectrum of those responses do you fall? Regardless of your answer, I’m going to pass on the advice of my mentor; &lt;em&gt;do not be a hero&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being in a romantic relationship with someone who has a mental illness definitely requires special considerations. In many ways, the good times will be better, but know that when the darkness creeps in, your partner will need an emotional rock to cling to until the storm passes. However, do not count out the regular rules of a relationship. While you may have to be there for the person more or extend more patience or empathy than being with someone who isn’t suffering from a mental illness, generally you know in your heart (or soul, or gut, or stomach, or some magical organ that provides emotional clarity) where you want to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This whole response probably could have fit on Twitter by removing a couple of words – Communication is key, push yourself to better understand her, don’t be a hero, follow your gut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have a question about mental illness?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tweet me &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/robertjdown&quot;&gt;@robertjdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take all of this with a grain of salt, they are just my opinions and may not be right for your situation. I am not a physician or licensed counselor. This blog is not intended as, and is not, a substitute for professional medical advice. If you are having thoughts of suicide or self-harm, contact the National Suicide Prevention online or by phone at 1-800-273-8255.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/biography-of-a-bipolar//posts/when-your-significant-other-has-bipolar-disorder</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/biography-of-a-bipolar//posts/when-your-significant-other-has-bipolar-disorder</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
